-==http://www.1000fr.com== 謦灵风软影视论坛荣誉出品 本字幕仅供学习交流 严禁用于商业用途
www.1000fr.com presents
福尔摩斯探案 之回归记
The Return of Shelock Holmes
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=- 校对: ptrpan
第四季 第二集
S4E02
魔鬼之足
The Devil's Foot
快到了
Almost there.
一个在Harley街的医生
What does a Harley Street specialist
凭什么知道我的健康状况呢?
know about my health?
福尔摩斯 听着
Listen, Holmes,
Moor Agar医生坚持要你彻底休息一下
Doctor Moor Agar insists you have a complete rests
否则你的身体就要完全垮掉了
if you wish to avoid an absolute breakdown.
海边的空气对你的健康有利
The sea air will do you the world of good.
你该独自旅行的 华生
You should have traveled alone, Watson.
胡说
Nonsense.
你在休假中
You're on holiday.
太美妙了 福尔摩斯 简直太美妙了
Why it's wonderful, Holmes, wonderful!
这里的景色真是壮观
The views are spectacular.
我们正处在
Well we're looking at the most dangerous piece
我国最险峻的一处海岸线
of coastline in the country.
你的朋友是位自然历史学家?
Your friend is a natural historian I presume?
大学时代的老相识
An old acquaintance from my college days.
我去看下行李
I'll see to the luggage.
谢谢
Thank you.
你好 先生
Good day to you, sir.
我想之后几周
I thought as we were going to be neighbors
我们会成为邻居
for the next few weeks
我应当来欢迎一下
I ought to say a few words of welcome.
真是客气
How very kind.
而且我当然渴望见到
And of course I've long wanted to meet
夏洛克 福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
先生 我真的很荣幸
It is indeed a pleasure, sir.
谢谢 但我是约翰 华生医生
Thank you but I'm Doctor John Watson.
哦
Oh.
请进
Come in.
这是我的好朋友 夏洛克 福尔摩斯
This is my good friend Sherlock Holmes.
非常抱歉我本该意识到
A thousand apologies, I should have realized.
请进吧 Roundhay先生
Do come in Mr. Roundhay.
我真是太蠢了
Very stupid of me.
您怎么知道我的名字的?
How did you know my name?
你对考古很感兴趣是吗?
You have an interest in archeology do you not?
你怎么知道的?
Why yes.
华生 你来继续...
Deduce, Watson, go on.
推理
Deduce.
你鞋尖上 膝盖下面
You've got mud on the points of your shoes
和右手上
and beneath your knees
都沾有泥土
and on the fingers of your right hand...
太精彩了
Splendid, splendid.
这说明你之前跪了一段时间在地上
Which indicates that you've knelt on the ground for a length of time.
华生 你越来越不可思议了
Oh Watson, you're coming along marvelously.
你是个左撇子园丁
You're a left-handed gardener.
还是考古专业的学生
You're a student of archeology.
你发表了一篇关于新石器时代
You've published a paper over theories
埋葬风俗的文章
surrounding the neolithic burial rites.
您 尊敬的Francis Roundhay 还是当地教区的牧师
You are the Reverend Francis Roundhay, vicar of the parish.
太惊人了 先生
Astonishing, sir.
-请坐 -谢谢
-Please sit down. -Thank you.
但左撇子...
But left-handed?
你拿钓绳的那只手
The hand with which you hold the troll.
完全正确
Exactly right.
每个细节都准确无误 但是你是怎么
Precise in every detail but how sir?
怎么知道
How?
教区牧师...
Vicar, vicar vic...
这本教区的杂志...
the parish magazine has...
村子就在这附近吗?
The village is nearby?
是的 沿着滨海小道就能走到
Oh yes just along the coastal path.
村子很偏僻 但能满足我们全部所需
It's secluded but it caters for all our needs.
那是最近的居所吗?
I suppose is that the nearest habitation?
不 不 还有Tregennis家的房子
No, no, the Tregennis Estate
就在内陆一英里处
is about a mile inland.
非常和善的一家
Very nice people
我相信他们会向你展示
and I'm sure they'll extend to you
康沃尔人的热情好客
some fine Cornish hospitality.
不过...
However,
我已经打扰你们太久了
I've imposed enough upon you for one day.
或许你们愿意
Perhaps you'd care to
来我的住处
come and have dinner with me
共进晚餐?
one evening at the vicarage.
那我们就要打扰到你和你的家人了
Oh then we should impose upon you and your family?
哦不会的 我是单身
Oh no alas, I have no family.
我和Tregennis先生住在一起
I live alone except for Mr. Tregennis,
他住其中的一间
who has a suite of rooms in the house.
他为什么不住在自家房子里?
But does he not live on the estate?
家庭不合
A family dispute.
他的妹妹和两个兄弟住在那儿
His sister and two brothers live there
但他选择搬出来
but he chooses to live apart.
去牧师家里共进晚餐
Do you know dinner at the vicarage
是个很好的主意
is a splendid idea.
我们得安排一下时间
We must arrange a date.
那是当然的 先生们
Yes, well of course gentlemen,
祝你们过得愉快
good day to you.
早上好
Good morning.
康沃尔人的热情好客
Cornish hospitality.
风化后凹凸不平的花岗岩
Weathered pitted slabs of granite.
古时的坟墓散布在
Ancient tombs scattered throughout
这个半岛冗长的岁月里
the lengthened breath of this peninsula.
就像大海
Like the sea.
我想死亡始终如影随形吧
I suppose death is always with us.
是啊
Quite so.
在康沃尔的这些日子里
Quite often during those days in Cornwall,
福尔摩斯常常独自出行
Holmes would stride out alone.
此地的神秘与魅力
The mystery and glamour of the place
以及被遗忘的民族留下的不祥之气
with its sinister atmosphere of forgotten nations
吸引着我这位朋友的想象力
appeal to the imagination of my friend.
他花很长时间漫步
He spent much of his time in long walks
独自冥想
and solitary meditation.
然而在一个早晨
One morning however,
我朋友的恢复疗养
my friend's convalescence
被粗暴地打断了
was violently interrupted.
先生们 我强烈建议你们求助于警方
Gentlemen I urge you to consult the police.
福尔摩斯是位病人
Holmes is a sick man.
是的 但在渐渐康复中 华生
Yes but getting better all the time, Watson.
是有紧急事件发生吧
This is a matter of some emergency.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes,
我们只能将您
we can only regard it
恰巧出现在此时此地
as a special Providence
看做是上天的特别眷顾
that you should chance to be here at this time,
因为在整个英格兰
for in all England
你是我们唯一真正需要的人
you are the one man we truly need.
我试图跟Trengennis先生
I tried to explain to Mr. Tregennis
和Roundhay先生解释
and Mr. Roundhay
说你在疗养
that you're in convalescence.
我相信他们一定赞成
Yes I'm sure they'll be very sympathetic,
请坐
please sit down.
谢谢
Thank you.
事实上
The fact is,
正如我向华生医生所解释的
as I've explained to Doctor Watson,
一件异常骇人的悲剧
the most extraordinary and tragic affair
昨晚发生在这里
has occurred here during the night.
洗耳恭听
You have my full attention.
我应该先介绍一下
Perhaps I had better say a few words first.
这位是我曾提到的
This is Mr. Tregennis,
Tregennis先生
of whom I spoke.
Tregennis先生昨晚
Now Mr. Tregennis spent last night
与他的兄弟
in the company of his brother,
George和Owen
George and Owen,
以及妹妹Brenda一同
and his sister Brenda,
在Tredannick Wartha的房子里
at their house of Tredannick Wartha.
他走的时候
He left them,
他们围坐在餐桌前玩牌
playing cards around the dining table
身体和精神状态都很好
in excellent health and spirits.
但他今天早上回去的时候
But on his return this morning
发现情形极其诡异
he discovered a truly bizarre state of affairs.
三个人 不论生者还是死者
All three both alive and dead,
脸上都保留着
retained upon their faces
极度恐惧的表情
an expression of the utmost horror.
死者呢?
Dead?
死于惊恐
A convulsion of terror.
惨不忍睹
It was dreadful to look upon.
房里还有其它人吗?
Was there any sign of anyone else in the house?
只有Porter女士
Only Mrs. Porter,
她是厨师兼管家
cook and housekeeper.
她昨晚睡得很沉
She had slept deeply
没听见任何声响
and heard no sound in the night.
有什么异常被遗漏了吗?
Is anything missing, disarranged?
没有 福尔摩斯先生
Nothing, Mr. Holmes.
是怎样的恐惧
What could possibly
能够让一位青年女子死亡
frighten a young woman to death
让两位壮汉疯掉呢?
and two strong men out of their senses?
嗯 会是什么呢
Yes what indeed.
福尔摩斯 我相信本地警方
Well I'm sure, Holmes, that the local police
将会得出结论
would have reached some conclusions.
但很可能是不正确的
However, erroneous they may be.
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
想一想
Think.
告诉我昨晚的情况 Tregennis先生
Tell me about last night, Mr. Tregennis.
好的 福尔摩斯先生
Well Mr. Holmes,
我在那里吃过晚饭
I supped there,
正如牧师所说
as the vicar has said,
之后我的哥哥George
and my elder brother George
提议玩一会儿扑克牌
proposed a game of whist afterwards.
我走的时候是十点一刻
It was a quarter-past ten when I moved to go.
谁送你出门?
Who let you out?
Potter夫人已经睡了
Mrs. Potter had gone to bed
所以我自己出了门
so I let myself out.
他们所处房间的窗户都关着
The window of the room in which they sat was closed,
但窗帘并没有拉上
but the blind was not drawn down.
今天早上
There was no change
门和窗子都和昨晚一样
in door or window this morning,
也没有理由怀疑
nor any reason to think
有陌生人进入过房子
that any stranger had been to the house.
他们就坐在原地
Yet there they sat,
完全被吓疯了
driven clean mad with terror.
在我有生之年我都无法
I'll never get the sight of that room
把那个房间的景象从我脑海中磨灭
out of my mind so long as I live.
是啊 事实总是最深刻的
Yes, the facts are most remarkable.
Tregennis先生你个人认为
Mr. Tregennis do you have any theory of your own
他们为何会遭此不幸?
which might account for them?
这是魔鬼
It is devilish.
魔鬼 福尔摩斯先生
Devilish, Mr. Holmes.
那力量不属于这个世界
It is not of this world.
如果这个事件已超出人类范畴
Well the matter is beyond humanity
那它自然也超出我的能力范围
it is certainly beyond me.
的确如此 福尔摩斯
I trust so, Holmes.
想想
Now think.
仔细想一想 Tregennis先生
Think very carefully, Mr. Tregennis,
昨晚你们在一起的时间里
about the evening that you spent together.
你记忆里有没有什么特别的事情
Does anything stand out in your memory
能为这场惨剧提供一点线索
which might throw some light upon this tragedy?
没有 福尔摩斯先生
There is nothing, Mr. Holmes.
他们是容易不安的人吗?
Were they nervous people?
他们曾表现出任何恐惧的预兆吗?
Did they ever show any sign of apprehension?
我认为没有 福尔摩斯先生
Not to my knowledge, Mr. Holmes.
那你就对我的探案没什么帮助了
Then there's nothing in which you can assist me.
我突然想起一件事
There is one thing occurs to me.
我坐在桌边的时候背对着窗户
As I sat at the table my back was to the window,
我的哥哥George
and my brother George,
玩牌的时候和我一伙
he being my partner at cards,
面朝窗户
was facing it.
我见他有一次从我肩上看过去
I saw him once look hard over my shoulder,
所以我也回头看了看
so I turned round and looked also.
窗帘没拉 窗户关着
The blind was up and the window shut,
我只能看到庭院里的矮树丛
but I could just make out the bushes on the lawn,
但有一个瞬间
and it seemed to me for a moment
我好像看到有什么东西在移动
that I saw something moving among them.
说不清那是人或动物
I couldn't even say if it was man or animal,
只是觉得有东西在那儿
but I just thought I saw something there.
你没想要弄清楚吗?
Did you not investigate?
当时认为没什么
Well the matter passed as unimportant.
你看到任何恶魔的迹象吗?
Did you have any premonition of evil?
我只是觉得
None that I was aware of.
你怎么会这么早
How did you hear the terrible news
就得知噩耗?
so early this morning?
我习惯早起
I am an early riser.
一般在早餐前散步
Generally take a walk before breakfast.
今早我刚刚出门
This morning I had hardly started
Richard医生
when Doctor Richard
驾着马车找到了我
overtook me in his carriage.
Tregennis先生
Mr. Tregennis.
我刚从你妹妹家得知了一条紧急消息
I've just heard an urgent message from your sister's house.
怎么了?
What's happened?
我不是很确定
I'm not quite sure, sir,
你最好还是跟我去一趟吧
but you'd better come with me.
她死了至少六个小时
She's been dead at least six hours.
没有施暴的痕迹
No signs of violence.
但为什么?
But how?
Tregennis先生 我从未见过这种情形
I've never seen the like, Mr. Tregennis.
这么多年来...
Not in all my years has a...
你还好吗?
You all right?
我来扶着你 过来...
I've got you. Here.
过来
Over here.
坐下
There we go.
他差点也在我们面前出事
We nearly got him on our hands as well.
你要去哪儿 福尔摩斯
Where are you going Holmes?
去Tredannick Wartha 不能耽搁
Tredannick Wartha without delay.
福尔摩斯先生
With your permission Mr. Holmes
请您允许我先走一步
I'll go on ahead.
谢谢你 牧师...快点
Thank you vicar, quickly,
否则我们就要比你先到了
otherwise we'll be there before you.
福尔摩斯 我必须劝阻你
Holmes, I must protest.
把你的劝阻留着吧 华生
Save your protestations for later, Watson,
多留一会儿
much later!
我想你因为某些原因
I gather you were divided
和你的家庭分开了
in some way from your family.
是的 福尔摩斯先生
Oh yes sir, Mr. Holmes.
那已经是过去的事情了
Well the matter is past and done with.
一切都已经被原谅和遗忘了
All was forgiven and forgotten
我们曾是最亲密的朋友
and we were the best of friends.
我们家曾在Redruth作锡矿工
We were a family of tin-miners at Redruth,
但我们把家族企业卖给了一家公司
but we sold out our venture to a company,
就此退休并有了足够的钱维持生计
and so retired with enough to keep us.
我不否认分家产的时候
I won't deny there was some bad feeling
有一些不愉快
over the division of the money.
彼此间的不睦有很多年了
It stood between us for a number of years.
不过
Nevertheless.
你决定不离开Cornwall?
You decided not to leave Cornwall?
我想我还怀着某天
I supposed I entertained
欣喜的回到家人身边的希望
some hopes of returning home one day.
福尔摩斯!
' Holmes!
福尔摩斯 快靠边!
Holmes, stand back!
我的兄弟们
My brothers.
他们要被送去Helston
They're taking them to Helston.
这房子真不错 Tregennis先生
It's a lovely house, Mr. Tregennis.
这是很悲伤的地方
It's a very sad house.
这就是你看到
This is the window
影子的那扇窗户
through which you saw the shadow form.
它距离窗户大概有多远?
Approximately what distance was it from the glass?
我想不少于10英尺
I'd say not less than ten feet.
我感觉
With a guess,
大概这么远
about here.
没有强迫闯入的迹象
There's no sign of a forced entry.
窗户当然是
And the window, of course,
一直锁着的
would have remained locked.
我妹妹查看它是否锁着
My sister made sure of that.
即便在Cornwall
Even in Cornwall.
太抱歉了
So dreadfully sorry.
没关系 福尔摩斯先生
It's quite all right, Mr. Holmes.
小意外
An accident.
谢谢
Thank you.
能告诉Porter夫人我回来了吗?
Could you let Mrs. Porter know I'm back?
我想见见管家
I should like to meet the housekeeper.
当然可以
Of course.
但请尽量避免
Oh but please try to avoid
再让她过于悲痛
causing further distress.
死亡总是悲痛的
Death is always distressing, Mr.Tregennis.
啊 椅子呢...
Awe, the chairs.
在警察离开这里后
Well they must have been moved
它们一定被移动过
after the police left the house.
那把是在这儿 福尔摩斯先生
That one here, Mr. Holmes.
这把在那儿
One over there.
这个在这儿
This one here.
这把在这儿
This one over here.
还有什么其他东西被移动过吗?
Has anything else been moved?
所有都跟我记忆中一样
All is as I remember it.
你一定了解
You must understand
今早我来这儿的时候
there was a great deal of fuss and confusion
是多么的忙乱和困惑
when I arrived this morning.
可能有东西被移动过
Things may have been moved
没有想到它们在
without thought given to their significance
犯罪调查中的重要性
in a criminal investigation.
犯罪?
Criminal?
这个词很有趣
That is a very interesting word.
这么说你又不赞成
So you no longer subscribe to the theory
所谓超自然的解释了?
of a supernatural explanation?
我不知道
I don't know.
大家是怎么坐的?
Where were people sitting?
我坐在这儿 面对着Georgie
I sat here facing Georgie,
我的哥哥
my brother George.
Brenda挨着我
Brenda sat next to me.
Owen对着她
Owen across from her.
哦 这很古怪
Oh that's curious.
怎么?
What?
我是说从这个位置看出去
I mean from this position
窗外的东西
the figure outside of the window
想必要超过6英尺
must have been well over six feet.
福尔摩斯先生 我只能如实 告诉你我所见到的
I can only tell you what I saw Mr. Holmes.
哦 这是我们的管家
Awe, this is my housekeeper,
Porter夫人
Mrs. Porter.
亲爱的 我想让你见一下这些先生们
I'd like you to meet these gentlemen, my dear.
她是那么美丽
She was so beautiful.
那么...美...丽
So beautiful.
她还是很难过
She is still very upset.
我们都很难过 Roundhay先生
We're all very upset Mr. Roundhay.
来坐下
Come and sit down.
我不会再留在这个房子里
I will not stay in this house
多一秒钟
one moment longer than I have to.
我要回到自己家去
So I shall rejoin my family.
但你也是我们家的一份子啊
But you're part of our family.
Tregennis一家已经不在了 先生
The family Tregennis is dead, sir.
至少是如死了一般
Dead or as good as.
我还活着呢
I'm still alive.
Porter夫人
Mrs. Porter,
不好意思
excuse me now.
Porter夫人
Mrs. Porter.
我叫夏洛克 福尔摩斯
My name is Sherlock Holmes
我希望你能告诉我所有你知道的事
and I'd like you to tell me all that you know.
福尔摩斯先生是位侦探
Mr. Holmes is a detective.
他是来想要找出
He's going to try and find out
Brenda发生了什么 别紧张
what happened to Brenda. Don't you worry.
请不要有所保留
Please, leave nothing out.
我只知道很少 福尔摩斯先生
I can tell you very little, Mr. Holmes.
你出老千
Awe, you've been cheating.
我没有
I am not cheating.
Owen 告诉你亲爱的妹妹
Owen will you tell your dearest sister
按规则玩牌
to play by the rules.
她也是你妹妹
Well she's your sister too.
你跟她说
You tell her.
但她是跟你一伙的
But she's on your side.
时候不早了
It's rather late
我得回牧师家了
and I do have to get back to the vicarage.
Mortimer 你晚上还是留宿在这里吧
Mortimer you must stay here for the night.
答应了吧
Oh please say you will.
那...
Well?
如果他不愿意就不要强迫他 Brenda
Don't force him to stay if he doesn't want to, Brenda.
哦 是吗
Oh really,
我以为我们的争执已经结束了呢
I thought we'd put an end to our squabbling.
Moritimer对我来说
Mortimer is just as much my brother
跟你和Georgie一样亲
as you and Georgie.
不用担心 兄弟们
Don't worry, dear brother,
我知道我不受欢迎
I know where I'm not welcome
那干嘛还来拜访我们
Why visit us at all.
是你离开了我们
You disowned us.
还是你已经忘了?
Or have you have forgotten?
Beth 这样就行了
It will be all right now, Beth,
你可以去就寝了
if you wish to retire.
Tregennis先生今晚会住在这里吗?
Is Mr. Tregennis staying with us tonight?
怎么了?
Why?
Porter夫人 你也不愿意我在这里吗?
Do you also object to my presence, Mrs. Porter?
Mortimer
Mortimer!
我想知道我用不用给你的房间通风
I want to know should I air your room, sir?
抱歉
Sorry.
谢谢你 Beth
Thank you, Beth.
这样就可以了
That'll be quite all right.
Tregennis不会留宿的
Mr. Tregennis will not be staying.
好的 Brenda小姐
Very good, Miss Brenda.
你们习惯于
Is it customary to have a fire in the room
这个时节在屋里点火吗?
at this time of year?
外面又湿又冷 福尔摩斯先生
It was a cold and damp night, Mr. Holmes.
我倒是觉得
Well I must say I...
这里是湿热
I thought it was rather humid.
我有轻微的血症
Oh I suffer with a mild blood disorder,
在温暖的夜晚也会觉得寒冷
feel the cold on even warm nights.
我知道你的感觉
I know how you feel.
Porter夫人
Awe, Mrs. Porter,
你今早来的时候
was the door to this room closed
门是锁着的吗?
when you left this morning?
当然 先生
Oh certainly, sir.
...夜莺在山谷下歌唱
...Nightingale as they sing in the valley below.
歌唱...
As they sing...
安置好他们后 我把窗户大开
When they were covered I threw wide the window
让早晨的空气透进来
to let in the morning air.
然后我跑到小路上
Then I run down to the lane
叫了个农夫去找大夫
and sent a farm lad for the doctor.
接下来的我想你已经知道了 先生
And the rest I think you know, sir.
Porter夫人说得对
Mrs. Porter's right.
她的确很美
She's very beautiful.
是啊 但有什么被遗漏了
Yes but something's missing.
Tregennis绝对没有轻微的血症
Tregennis is lying about a mild blood disorder;
我以我的名誉担保
I'll state my reputation on that.
是吗?
Was he?
华生
Watson.
看这个
Look at this.
这很罕见
That's very unusual.
这不可能
It won't do!
三个人因为某种有意
Three people grievously stricken
或无意的人类行动 而受到极度惊吓
by some conscious or unconscious human agency.
那么
Now,
事件确切发生在什么时候呢?
when exactly did this event occur?
他们打完牌
They're finished playing cards.
已经过了他们通常就寝的时间
It was past their usual hour for bed.
椅子并没有
The panel of the chairs
被推到桌子下面
had not been pulled back from the table.
那么应该就在
Then it must have been
Tregennis离开之后不久
only moments after Tregennis left the house.
对
Exactly.
当然 你一定注意到了
Your conscious, of course,
我设法得到了
I've managed to obtain
他的清晰脚印
a clear imprint of his foot.
嗯 看见了
Yes I saw.
得到了他的脚印
Haven got a sample print
我就能从其他脚印中鉴别出他的
I could pick out his tracks among the others
从而判断他的行踪
and follow his boots.
根据他的步幅
For the length of his stride
他很快就回到了牧师家中
he returns swiftly to the vicarage.
Tregennis离开后
Tregennis disappeared
几乎立刻
then almost instantly
某人就让兄妹三人受了惊吓
some other person affected the card players.
我们该如何推测这个人是谁呢?
How can we reconstruct that person?
华生 有什么确凿证据证明
But is there any evidence really, Watson
的确有人爬上了窗户吗?
that anyone did creep up to that window?
唯一的暗示来自于Tregennis
The only suggestion comes from Tregennis,
说他哥哥感觉
who says that his brother reacted
花园里有动静
to some movement in the garden.
那这种恐怖
Then how was this
是如何散布的?
impression of horror conveyed?
你就是那个侦探 夏洛克 福尔摩斯?
You're Mr. Sherlock Holmes the detective.
你就是 Leon Sterndale医生
And you are Doctor Leon Sterndale,
伟大的猎狮者
the great lion-hunter
以及著名的非洲探险家
and famous African explorer.
有什么进展吗?
Have you made any progress?
一些
Some.
本郡警方全然错误
The county police are utterly at fault.
告诉我关于Tregennis一家的事件
Tell me what you know
你知道些什么
about the fate of the Tregennis family.
Sterndale医生 你为什么感兴趣呢?
What is your interest, Dr. Sterndale?
希望我这样说你能相信
My claim to be taken into your confidence
由于我常常居于此地
is that during my many residences here
对于Tregennis一家
I have come to know
很了解
this family of Tregennis very well.
事实上从我同是康沃尔人的母亲这边算来
Indeed upon my Cornish mother's side
他们是我的表亲
I may call them cousins.
所以他们的不幸遭遇
So their strange fate
自然使我很震惊
has naturally been a great shock to me.
你知道任何能够
Do you know of anything
帮助我们调查的事情吗?
that could help us out in the inquiry?
没有
Nothing at all.
可以告诉你 我得到消息的时候
I may tell you that I had got as far as Plymouth
正在Plymouth
upon my way to Africa
本打算前往非洲
when news reached me.
但我直接回到这里
I came straight back here
来看看我有什么能帮忙的
to help in any way I can.
你误了船期了吗?
Did you lose your boat?
我会乘下一班
I will take the next.
这真是深厚的友谊啊
That is friendship indeed.
我说过了 我们是亲戚
I tell you they were relatives.
你的行李已经上船了吗?
Did your baggage go on with boat?
一些
Some of it,
但还有一些在旅馆里
but most of it remained in the hotel.
显然这个事件不会出现在
Well surely this event could not have
Plymouth的晨报上
found its way into the Plymouth morning papers.
是的 先生
No, sir
我接到了电报
I received a telegram.
谁发的?
From whom?
你真会刨根问底啊 福尔摩斯先生
You are very inquisitive, Mr. Holmes.
这是我的工作
It is my business.
Roundhay牧师发的电报
The vicar, Mr. Roundhay sent it,
叫我回来
recalling me back.
了解了
I see.
我可以问一下你是否
May I ask if your suspicions
有特别怀疑的对向?
point in any particular direction?
我很难回答
Well I can hardly answer that.
那这是在浪费我的时间了
Then I'm wasting my time.
在缺少线索的情况下动脑思考
To work the brain without sufficient material
就像是引擎空转
is like racing an engine,
它自己就会分崩离析
it cracks itself to pieces.
在住处等我
Wait for me at the cottage.
你要去哪儿?
Where are you going?
高兴点 华生
Cheer up, Watson!
海风 阳光 耐性
Sea air, sunshine, patience,
一切都会真相大白
all will be revealed.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes!
Mr. Holmes.
福尔摩斯先生
福尔摩斯先生 我们是鬼上身了
Mr. Holmes, we are devil ridden, Mr. Holmes.
我这可怜的教区是鬼上身了
My poor parish is devil-ridden!
怎么了?
What has happened?
约三小时前死亡
Dead about three hours I'd say.
症状与Brenda Tregennis完全相同
Same symptoms exactly as Brenda Tregennis.
四肢抽搐 手指扭曲
Limbs convulsed, fingers contorted
就像死于突发的恐惧
as though he died from a very paroxysm of fear.
这不该发生在我的屋檐下
That it should happen under my roof.
他睡过了吗?
Has his bed been slept in?
是的 应该是
Oh yes, most definitely.
谁打开的窗户?
Who opened this window?
我的管家
My housekeeper,
她是今早第一个进入这个房间的人
she was the first into the room this morning.
她现在在哪?
Where is she now?
她头疼得很厉害于是卧床休息了
Oh she's taken to her bed with a severe headache,
毫无疑问
no doubt.
受惊吓所致
Greatly affected by the shock.
对于给您带来的不便
I am most terribly sorry
我感到十分抱歉
to inconvenience you in this way.
我知道你们是来这里度假 但是...
I know you both came to these parts to rest but...
想让福尔摩斯不插手是很难的
It isn't easy with Holmes around.
他最喜欢让自己投身于
He likes nothing better than to sink his teeth
这种事件
into a problem of this sort.
但是两场死亡
But two deaths,
华生先生
Doctor Watson,
发生在两天之内
in the space of two days.
这毫无疑问
This is the work of the devil,
是魔鬼作祟
make no mistake.
还是相信已知和切实的东西吧
Put your faith in the known and tangible,
Roundhay先生
Mr. Roundhay.
现场没有被破坏过是吗?
I trust nothing has been touched, sir?
是的 一切完好如初
No, everything's exactly as it was.
好的
All right then.
我需要你和你的管家
I'll need a statement
做一份口供
from you and your housekeeper.
警官 我很抱歉她还病着
Master, I'm afraid she's still rather ill.
检查下楼上
Check up stairs.
这些人是谁?
Who are these gentlemen?
哦 来自伦敦的夏洛克 福尔摩斯先生
Oh, Mr. Sherlock Holmes
和华生医生
and Doctor Watson from London.
我听过您的大名 福尔摩斯先生
I've heard of you Mr. Holmes.
如果你能将此事件的调查留给警方 我将不胜感激
I'd appreciate it if you would leave this inquiry to the official police.
如您所愿
As you wish.
正是我愿
I do sir.
不好意思
I'm sorry.
你能将警官的注意力引到
Would you direct the inspector's attention
楼上的窗户
towards the window upstairs
和桌子上的台灯上吗?
and the lamp on the table?
这都是重要线索
Each is suggestive.
有这两样 他们就差不多能得出结论了
Together they are almost conclusive.
华生
Watson?
下午好
Good afternoon.
祝你好运
Good luck.
你到底在做什么?
What on earth are you doing?
实验
An experiment
验证一个理论
to test a theory.
这不是Tregennis房间的台灯吗?
Isn't that the lamp that was in Tregennis' room?
是也不是
Yes and no.
我看到你买了个一模一样的
I see you bought an identical one.
我是从村子里
I purchased it from
一家可爱的小商铺买的
a delightful little shop in the village.
你整个下午就是去那儿了
That's where you've been all afternoon.
我们听到的两个事件
There is a single point of resemblance
有一个共同之处
in the reports that we've heard.
关键在于第一个发现
Now this concerns of the effect
案件的人进入房间时
on the atmosphere of the room
所感觉到的屋内气氛
upon those who first entered it.
首先是Richards先生
First Doctor Richards
而后是Porter夫人
then Mrs. Porter.
还有Roundhay的管家
And Roundhay's housekeeper
今早也病了
was taken ill this morning.
每个案件中
In each case
都有东西
there is a combustion
在房内燃烧
going in the room.
第一个 是炉火
In the first case, a fire.
第二个 是灯
In the second, a lamp.
炉火可能是必须的
Now the fire perhaps was necessary
但在天色大亮的时候 灯还点着
but the lamp was lit when it was already broad daylight.
我将这个灯所耗的油与
The comparison of the oil consumed in this
Tregennis的灯做了比较证明了这一点
and Tregennis' lamp proves that point.
但 为什么?
But why?
某种物质燃烧
Something was burned
生成某种气体
producing an atmosphere
并导致了奇特的中毒效应
and causing a strange toxic affect.
第一个案件中
In the first instance,
在Tregennis家里
that of the Tregennis family,
这种物质被放在炉火里
a substance was placed in the fire
炉火会使烟雾
and the fire would carry the fumes,
在某种程度上扩散到烟囱里
to some extent, up the chimney.
只有Brenda Tregennis
Only Brenda Tregennis,
离炉火最近
was closest to the fire,
最后死亡
was killed.
她的兄弟表现为精神错乱
Her brothers were exhibiting that lunacy,
显然都是毒药的初步作用
which is evidently the first effect of the drug.
当然另外一个案件里
The other case of course
是被得逞了
the result was complete.
这么说是一种
So it's a poison,
燃烧时发生作用的毒药?
which works by combustion?
是的
Yeah.
一个明显的地方就是
The obvious place to look
Tregennis房间里
was the smoke-guard of the lamp
灯的防烟罩
in Tregennis' room.
在那 不出所料
There, sure enough,
我发现了一些灰末
I perceived a number of flaky ashes
并在灯的边缘发现了一些
and round the edges a fringe of brownish powder,
未烧尽的褐色粉末
which had not yet been consumed.
我取走了一半
Half of it I took,
留了另一半给警方
the other half I left for the police.
我们来看看
We will see
能否在我们的灯上
if we can reproduce the same effects
产生同样的效果
with our own lamp.
不行 福尔摩斯 这简直是疯了
Oh no, Holmes, that's insane.
我不能强迫你留在这里
I cannot force you to stay
但是我要找到答案
but I mean to have the answer.
当然我要留下
Of course I shall stay.
我想我了解我的华生
I thought I knew my Watson.
把门打开好吗?
Would you open the door please?
请坐在这里
Now would you like to just sit there?
准备好了吗?
Are you ready?
福尔摩斯先生 你必须保持清醒
You must stay clear Mr. Holmes
否则会被踩在脚下
or be trampled underfoot.
福尔摩斯
Holmes!
福尔摩斯 能听见我说话吗?
Holmes, can you hear me?
看在上帝的份上 能听见我吗?
For God's sake can you hear me?
成功!
Done!
谢天谢地你还好
Thank God your all right.
这真是愚蠢而危险的行径
That was a stupid and dangerous thing to do.
我们可能会因此丧命
We could have been killed.
这是个不理智的实验
It was an unjustifiable experiment
即便是对自己而言 更何况是对朋友
even for myself, doubly so for a friend.
我真的非常抱歉
But really I'm extremely sorry.
所有的证据都指向Tregennis
All the evidence points to Tregennis
他是第一个案件的罪犯
being the criminal in the first tragedy
也是第二个案件的受害者
and victim in the second.
是的 如果是其他人进入房间
Yes, if anyone else would have come in
那家人就会从桌旁站起来
the family would have certainly risen from the table.
那么Tregennis是自杀?
Then Tregennis' own death was suicide?
那是Leon Sterndale
That will be Doctor Leon Sterndale.
能请他进来吗 华生?
Would you let him in, Watson?
请进 Sterndale医生
Please come in, Doctor Sterndale.
好像你被料到会来
Seems your expected.
我一小时前收到你的便条
I had your note about an hour ago.
但恕我直言
But let me state directly,
我对召唤自己的人向来粗鲁
I don't take kindly to being summoned by anybody.
我们还是在这儿谈一下案件情况
I thought it better to discuss the matter here.
没有被偷听的危险
No risk of eavesdropping.
我不明白 先生
I fail to see, sir,
你所说的
what you can have to speak about
与我私人
which affects me personally
密切相关的事情
in the most intimate fashion.
Mortimer Tregennis的死
The killing of Mortimer Tregennis.
我长期与野人为伴
I have lived so long among savages
不受法律约束
and beyond the law
而我已经习惯于
that I've got into the way
自己就是法律
of being a law unto myself.
福尔摩斯先生 你最好还是
You would do well, Mr. Holmes,
不要忘记
to remember that,
我并不想加害于你
for I have no desire to do you any injury.
我也不想加害于你
Nor I you,
Sterndale医生
Doctor Sterndale.
最好的证明就是
But surely the clearest proof of it is that,
尽管我知道了一切
knowing what I know,
我找了您
that I have sent for you
而不是警察
and not for the police.
如果你是在愚弄我 先生
If this is a bluff upon your part, sir,
那你真是找错实验对象了
you have chosen the wrong man for your experiment.
不不 愚弄人的是你
No, no, no the bluff is upon your side
而不是我
not upon mine.
现在我来说说
Now I will tell you the facts
我得出结论的事实依据
upon which my conclusions are based.
你从Plymouth回来时
Of your return from Plymouth,
把一些行李
allowing much of your property
运到了非洲
to go out to Africa,
这提醒了我
I shall say nothing except that it informed me
你是构成
was that you were one of the factors,
这一戏剧性事件的
which had to be taken into account
重要因素之一
in reconstructing of this drama.
旅馆的这封电报
This telegram from the hotel
证实了你对我所说的
confirms what you told me.
我们上次相遇的时候
Now when we last met
你问我怀疑谁
you asked me whom I suspected
而我拒绝回答
and I refused to answer you.
接着你就离开了
Then you departed
但你并没有回家
but you didn't go home,
没有 Sterndale医生
oh no Doctor Sterndale,
你去了牧师的住处
you went to the vicarage
在那儿等了一会儿
and you waited there for some time.
你是怎么知道的?
How do you know that?
我跟踪了你
I followed you.
我谁也没看见
I saw no one.
我跟踪你
That is what you may expect to see
自然不愿被你看见
when I follow you.
你彻夜未眠
You spent a restless night.
制定了一个计划
You made certain plans
准备第二天
and then in the early hours
清晨执行
you proceeded to put them into action.
你回到牧师的家
You returned to the vicarage.
在悬崖小路上拾了几颗
Collected some distinctive red gravel
特别的红色石子
from the cliff path.
天已大亮
The house by now was daylight
但屋里还没有动静
but the inhabitants were not stirring.
你朝Tregennis的窗户
You threw some of the red gravel
扔了几颗红色石子
up at the window of Tregennis.
Sterndale
Sterndale.
我必须马上跟你谈谈
I must speak with you urgently.
现在?
This hour?
门锁着
The doors are locked.
管家拿着钥匙
The housekeeper has the keys.
这事至关重大
It is of the utmost importance!
你从开着的窗子进去
You entered through the sitting window.
你们进行了很短的会谈
You had an interview, a short one,
你在屋子里来回踱步
and you walked up and down the room.
他对你的到来害怕了
He withdrew as you had come.
你当时穿着和现在脚上
You wearing the same pair of studied walking shoes,
一样的步行鞋
which at the present moment are upon your feet
而Mortimer Tregennis死了
and Mortimer Tregennis was dead.
你送给Brenda Tregennis的戒指
The ring you gave Brenda Tregennis.
是的
Yes.
Brenda Tregennis
Brenda Tregennis.
多年来我深爱着她
For years I loved her.
她也深爱着我
For years she loved me.
这就是人们所惊奇的
There is the secret of the Cornish seclusion,
我隐居在康沃尔的秘密所在
which people so marveled at.
这样我才能接近
It brought me close to
这个世界上
the one person on this earth
我最心爱的人
who was dear to me.
我不能娶她
I couldn't marry her,
尽管妻子离开我多年
for I had a wife who left me for whom,
但因为英格兰可悲的法律
by the deplorable laws of England,
我不能离婚
I could not divorce.
多年来Brenda一直等待着
For years Brenda waited.
多年来我一直等待着
For years I waited.
然而这竟是我们等来的结果
And this is what we waited for.
Roundhay知道这秘密
Roundhay knew.
我们信任他
He was in our confidence,
因此他拍电报到Plymouth告诉我
hence his telegram to me at Plymouth.
当我得知心上人
What was my baggage or Africa to me
遭此不幸时
when I learned that such a fate
行李和非洲对我又算得了什么呢?
had befallen my darling?
你就是这么得知我
There you have the missing clue
不为人知的秘密吧 福尔摩斯先生
to my actions, Mr. Holmes.
我知道你 先生
I understand that you sir,
你是位医生?
are a doctor of medicine?
你听过'Radix pedis diaboli'这种制剂吗?
Have you ever heard of 'Radix pedis diaboli'?
魔鬼脚跟
Devils foot root.
没有 从未听过
No I can't say that I have.
这不能怪你的专业知识
Well there's no reflection upon your professional knowledge
我相信 除了放在Buda某实验室的一份
for I believe that, save for one sample in a laboratory at Buda,
欧洲再没有其他样本了
there is no other specimen in Europe.
这被西非某些地区的医师用作
It is used as an ordeal poison by the medicine men
刑讯的毒药
in certain districts of West Africa
并被严加保管
and it is kept as a secret by them.
你已经知道很多事了 福尔摩斯先生
You already know so much, Mr. Holmes;
但还是让我把全部事实告诉你为好
it is clearly to my interest that you should know all.
我已经解释过
I have already explained
我和Tregennis家族的关系
the relationship in which I stood
他们家曾因财产而发生过争吵
to the Tregennis family.
因此与Mortimer疏远了
There had been quarrel about money,
他是个阴险狡诈的家伙
which estranged this man Mortimer,
但因为Brenda的缘故
a sly, subtle, scheming man,
我对她的哥哥很友善
but for Brenda's sake
几周前的一天
I was friendly with her brother.
他来到我的住处
Then one day a few weeks ago
我给他展示了一些非洲珍奇
he came to my cottage
除了别的
and I showed him some of my African curiosities.
我还给他展示了"魔鬼之足"
Among other things,
这是毒药?
I exhibited the Devil's foot.
难以置信
Poison you say?
你没试过不会相信的
Fascinating.
一点点就能够致命
You wouldn't think so if you were to try it.
这种粉末
The smallest amount could be fatal.
在燃烧时会即刻反应
In this powder form
刺激大脑中枢
it reacts instantaneously when burned.
控制恐惧情感的区域
It stimulates those brain centers,
非疯即死
which control the emotion of fear.
那些不幸的本地人
Madness or death
若是遭受部落医师的折磨
is the fate of the unfortunate native
就是这样的下场
who is subjected to the ordeal
会被发现吗?
by the priest of his tribe.
欧洲科学是不能的
Can it be detected?
几天后
Not by European science.
我的住处有人闯空门
A few days later
但貌似什么都没拿
my cottage was broken into
我没有留意
but since nothing seemed to have been taken
直到Roudhay先生的电报
I gave the matter no heed
到达Plymouth
until Mr. Roundhay's telegram
Mortimer这个恶棍
arrived at Plymouth.
以为我得知消息的时候
This villain, Mortimer,
已经在海上
had thought that I would be at sea
并一去非洲很多年
before news reached me,
但我当然立刻回来
and that I should be lost for years in Africa.
我一听到详细情况
But of course I returned immediately
就能断定
and I could not hear the details
他用的正是我的毒药
without being assured that it was my poison, which had been used,
而Mortimer Tregennis本人
and that Mortimer Tregennis himself
就是凶手
was the murderer.
我一心要报仇
My sole cried out for revenge.
你杀了她!
You murdered her!
为了钱你杀了自己的亲妹妹!
For money you murdered your own sister.
你没有证据
You can't prove that.
当地陪审团不会相信你
No jury in the land will believe you.
我就是陪审团 Tregennis
I'm my own jury, Mr. Tregennis.
法官 陪审团和刽子手
Judge, jury and executioner.
我点燃了台灯
I lit the lamp.
把粉末放到上面
I put the powder above it.
五分钟后他死了
In five minutes he died.
上帝啊
My God!
死状其惨
How he died!
但我不为所动
But my heart was flint,
因为他仅仅是经历了
for he endured nothing
我无辜的心上人
which my innocent darling
之前所经历的一切
had not suffered before him.
你可以采取任何行动 福尔摩斯先生
You can take what steps you like, Mr. Holmes.
但没有什么谁
But there can be no man living
会比我现在更无惧死亡了
who fears death less than I do now.
你原本是怎么计划的?
What where your plans?
我打算把自己葬在中非
I was intending to bury myself in Central Africa.
那儿的工作只进行了一半
My work there is but half done.
那就去完成另外一半吧
Go and do the other half.
我个人不打算阻止你
I, for one, am not prepared to stop you.
上帝保佑你
God bless you,
你们两位
both of you.
已经不是第一次了 福尔摩斯
Not for the first time, Holmes,
把法律玩弄于股掌之上
you presume to take the law into your hands.
我从未爱过
I have never loved
但如果有过
but if I did
如果这个我爱的女人
and if the woman I had loved
遭此不幸
had met with such an end
我可能也会跟我们
I might act even as our
无视法律的猎狮者有相同的举动
lawless lion-hunter has done.
你不会吗?
Wouldn't you?
嗯 可能吧
Yes, I suppose so
但这不是关键
but that's not the point.
关键是我为什么要做警方的工作呢?
The point is why should I do the work of the official police?
而且正如你所言
And as your very fond of telling me,
我在休假中
I'm on holiday!
风软FRM字幕组作品 -==http://www.1000fr.com==- 欢迎加入
welcome to www.1000fr.com